## **CANER DERICI**

#### ABD PhD Candidate, Computer Science, Programming Languages

@ cderici@iu.edu

UT, USA

% cderici.github.io

github.com/cderici

Extended version (CV): cderici.github.io/cv.html

## **SELECTED PROJECTS**

#### Pycket: A tracing JIT compiler for self-hosting Racket<sup>1</sup>

• PhD project on Programming Languages. I am the main developer since 2016. I re-designed the compiler front-end to make Racket bootstrap on Pycket, i.e., achieved a full Racket implementation on RPython framework. Developed performance analysis/debugging tools, theoretical models, implemented various optimizations and large number of run-time primitives. Maintained and improved the run-time data structure implementations (hash tables, vectors, structs etc.).

#### Rax: A full-stack nanopass compiler from a small subset of Racket to x86\_64 assembly <sup>2</sup>

• Started for school, turned into a growing fun project. Twoperson collaboration. I built and tested all the passes (e.g., closure conversion, register allocation, code-gen, etc.).

#### FARS: Functional Automated Reasoning System<sup>3</sup>

• A resolution-refutation style automated theorem prover. I developed it for fun at first, then I turned it into a school project. Written all in Racket by myself.

#### HazirCevap (Witty): A closed domain question answering system for high school students

 MSc project on Natural Language Processing. I led the research and development, 3 faculty members and 4 grad students were involved. This was my MSc thesis work (see Publications). I developed a hybrid model for question analyzing (Hidden Markov Model along with a rule-based model), developed a reliability score for web-pages/documents, used the Indri search engine for processing and retrieval for answer generation, implemented both the front and back-end in Python.

#### Sessizliğe Oku (Read to Silence): An application to teach people with hearing disability how to read

• I was the main developer. 2 faculty members from Linguistics, 1 from CS, and 2 RAs were involved. We aimed to develop a stable framework, so Turkish grammar lectures and exercises could be easily accessible for Deaf people. Collaborated with the linguists to implement a web & mobile app specifically designed for Deaf people. Used JavaScript, HTML and PhoneGap.

## PUBLICATIONS

- Flatt M., Derici C. Dybvig R. K., Keep A. et. al. "Rebuilding racket on chez scheme (experience report)", ICFP'19
- Derici C. et. al. "A closed-domain question answering framework using reliable resources to assist students" Natural Language Engineering'18
- Derici C. et. al. "Question analysisfor a closed domain guestion answering system", CICLING'15
- Derici C. et. al. "Rule-basedfocus extraction in Turkish question answering systems", SIU'14
- Başar R. E., Derici C., and Şenol Ç. "World With Web: A compiler from world applications to JavaScript". Technical Report, Scheme and Functional Programming Workshop'09
  - <sup>1</sup>http://www.github.com/pycket/pycket
  - <sup>2</sup>https://github.com/cderici/rax
  - <sup>3</sup>https://github.com/cderici/FARS

#### **EDUCATION**

- PhD (Grad. 2021), CS, Indiana University, USA
- PhD CS, Boğaziçi University, Turkey (Dropped)
- MSc CS, Boğaziçi University, Turkey
- BSc CS, Istanbul Bilgi University, Turkey

## TECH SKILLS

Racket/Scheme/Lisp **Python** Java **JavaScript** C/C++ Haskell

SQL, Matlab, R, CSS

Linux

Git/Hg/Version Control Maven/Jenkins/Auto Deploy **Travis/Continuous Integration** 

**LATEX Emacs** 



### **EXPERIENCE**

- Course Instructor, Indiana University, Spring 2021. Introduction to Computer Science (HtDP Style Functional Programming).
- Teaching & Research Assistant, Indiana University, 2015 - 2020. Taught Advanced Compilers, Domain Specific Language Design, etc.
- Product Development Specialist, Asseco SEE. 2013. Developed and tested virtual point-ofsale applications. Used Java, Tomcat, Spring, Mercurial, Jira.
- Teaching Assistant, Istanbul Bilgi University, 2010 - 2013. Taught Data Structures & Algorithms, Programming Language Principles, Database Systems.
- Hackathonist'14, Istanbul, 2014. Developed a Google Glass application (running on a mock glass API) that talks with the CitySDK for various smart city tasks (e.g., finding a suitable bus-route).

# AWARDS & SCHOLARSHIPS

- Full Scholarship for BSc, 2005-2010
- Research Scholarship for MSc (fully funded for 2 years)
- Scholarship for a research project on teaching natural languages to hearing impaired, 2014.

## SPOKEN LANGUAGES

Turkish (native) English (living in US since 2015)

